Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Records; Records apap324
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Records
1963-2011
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty
apap324
0.6 cubic ft.
The Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (ICADP) formed in 1976 as the Illinois Coalition Against the Death Penalty by Mary Alice Rankin and other activist groups and organizations to try to prevent passage of capital punishment legislation in Illinois. After the state adopted the death penalty in 1977, ICADP expanded its grassroots legislative, education, and communication activities to try to inform the public about flaws and injustices in the Illinois capital punishment system and promote humane alternatives to the death penalty.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty donated its materials in 2011 to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
The Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (ICADP) formed in 1976 as the Illinois Coalition Against the Death Penalty by Mary Alice Rankin and other activist groups and organizations to try to prevent passage of capital punishment legislation in Illinois. After the state adopted the death penalty in 1977, ICADP expanded its grassroots legislative, education, and communication activities to try to inform the public about flaws and injustices in the Illinois capital punishment system and promote humane alternatives to the death penalty.
ICADP helped have a dramatic impact on the successes in the Illinois capital punishment conversation, promoting campaigns that highlighted flaws with the death penalty to the public and legislators in the state and forming strong bonds with other groups that also believed the abolishment of the death penalty is the best solution for the public. These groups included the Illinois Bar Association, ACLU, Amnesty International, Catholic Conference, Jewish Council on Urban Affairs, League of Women Voters and others.
In March 2011, ICADP’s campaign succeeded in passing legislation that repealed the death penalty in the state, and as of July 1st, 2011, Illinois became the sixteenth state to be death penalty-free.
ICADP’s work is not finished. Recently members of the Illinois legislature introduced bills in the General Assembly to reinstate capital punishment. ICADP is now focused on fighting reinstatement efforts and maintaining a death penalty-free state.
Scope and Contents
The Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (ICADP) donated its records in 2011 following repeal of the death penalty in the state. The archivist retained the original order of the files and the collection includes annual reports, newsletters, clippings and press releases. ICADP gained national attention with its campaign to rid Illinois of capital punishment; this is evident with materials documenting the case of John Wayne Gacy, executed in 1994, and the murder of nine year old Jeanine Nicarico in 1983.
The collection also contains the 2002 documentary film Too Flawed to Fix: The Illinois Death Penalty Experience which explores the legal flaws in the capital punishment system in Illinois and materials pertaining to Amnesty International. There are clippings of Northwestern University School of Law’s National Conference on Wrongful Convictions and the Death Penalty during which former Death Row inmates later found innocent of their crimes participated on a panel. In addition, the collection features clippings about the 2000 moratorium on the death penalty by Governor George H. Ryan and the 2011 signing of the bill SB 3539, Abolition of the Death Penalty, by Governor Pat Quinn.
There are materials related to key ICADP members Mary Alice Rankin, Miriam Wilson, and Dick Cunningham.
For additional files pertaining to ICADP, please see its collection at the University of Illinois at Chicago’s Richard J. Daley Library of Special Collections and Archives: http://www.uic.edu/depts/lib/findingaids/MSICAD11.html.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Capital punishment--Illinois; Death Penalty; Capital punishment--Moral and ethical aspects; Executions (Law)--United States--Cases; Illinois; Chicago (Ill.); Clippings; Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); Quinn, Pat; Ryan, George H.; Illinois Coalition Against the Death Penalty; Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty; Amnesty International; American Civil Liberties Union; Illinois. Governor's Commission on Capital Punishment
- Annual Meeting Flier, Benefit Flier, and Membership Card, 2009; 2010; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 1)
- Annual Reports, 2004; 2006; 2008; 2010 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 2)
- "Beyond Repair" Suburban Speaking Tour, 2010 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 3)
- Brochures, Newsletters, and Report on Activities, 2001; 2005-2007; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 4)
- Charles Walker-First Illinois Execution in 28 Years, 1990; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 5)
- Death Penalty Moratorium- Clippings and Press, 2000 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 6)
- "Disarming the State's Lethal Weapon" A Look at the Death Penalty Journey Problems, Flaws, Reforms and Moratorium, 2002 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 7)
- Events, Photos, and Copies of Petitions, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 8-9)
- Fact Sheets on the Repeal of the Death Penalty, 2006; 2011 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 10)
- Founding Materials, Dick Cunningham Memorial, and Tenth Anniversary of ICADP Celebration, 1976-1977; 1986; 2001; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 11)
- Governor Quinn's Office Announcement of the Abolition of the Death Penalty in Illinois, Remarks from the Floor of the House Assembly, 2011 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 12)
- Grant Proposals, 1983; 1987; 1989 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 13)
- Illinois ' Death Penalty: Too Flawed to Fix- Resource Manual, 1985 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 14)
- John Wayne Gacy- Execution Materials, Press Packet, and Clippings, 1994; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 15)
- Letters Commending Governor George H. Ryan on the Death Penalty Moratorium, 2002 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 16)
- Media Materials- Clippings, 1963-1989; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 17)
- Media Materials- Clippings, 1993-1998; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 18)
- Media Materials- Clippings, Internet Articles, 2002-2007 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous Materials, 2003; 2006; 2009 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 20)
- Mission Statement of ICADP, Amnesty International Events and Fliers, 1991-2002; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 21)
- Newsletters, 1990-1997; 2008-2010; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 22)
- Nicarico Case- Press Releases and News Clippings, 1985-1997; Undated (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 23)
- Post Repeal Records, 2011 (Box 1 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 24)
- Press Releases, 2000-2006 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 1)
- Prison Visit Materials for Both Inmates and ICADP Members, 2000; 2002; 2003; Undated (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 2)
- Prosecutorial Misconduct Clippings, 1999; 2000 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 3)
- Report of the Commission on Capital Punishment- Governor George H. Ryan, 2002 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 4)
- Road Trip for Justice Materials, 2004 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 5)
- Speaking Events, 2010 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 6)
- Strategic Planning, 2010 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 7)
- Testimony in Favor of Abolishing the Death Penalty and the Passing of the Bill SB 3539, 2011 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 8)
- Too Flawed to Fix, 2002 (Video-tape 1)
- Too Flawed to Fix Study Guide and Documentary Advertisement, 2002 (Box 2 (Illinois Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Re), Folder 9)